A Guide to the Papers of Thomas Perkins Abernethy, 1917-1973
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Thomas Perkins Abernethy 1917-1973
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
This collection consists of ca. 400 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers were presented to the library on June 3, 1975 by Thomas Perkins Abernethy through Mrs. Charles M. Davison, Jr.
Scope and Content Information
The latest addition to the Thomas Perkins Abernethy Collection consists of approximately four hundred items spanning the years 1917 through 1973. The material contained in this portion is very similar to the material in collections #6464-a and #6464-b and includes correspondence with colleagues in the history profession, former students, and members of the Abernethy family, as well as correspondence between Abernethy and his wife Ida (Robertson) Abernethy. Manuscripts for articles by both Abernethy and his wife, miscellaneous papers, and a large number of newspaper clippings comprise the rest of the collection.
Organization
The material has been organized like the addition #6464-b. That is, professional correspondence - correspondence with students, historians, and publishers - has been placed at the beginning of the collection, followed by personal correspondence - correspondence with relatives and friends unconnected with the history profession. All of the correspondence is in chronological order. Articles, research material, miscellaneous papers, and newspaper clippings follow the correspondence.
Contents List
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. Abernethy 1917, 1928-1929 (Box 1)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. Abernethy 1932-1938 (Box 1)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. Abernethy 1945, 1948 (Box 1)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. Abernethy 1950-1952, 1954-1956, 1959 (Box 1)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. Abernethy 1960-1973 & n.d., 9 folders (Box 1)
- Personal Correspondence of T. P. and Ida (Robertson) Abernethy 1918-1921, 1926-1928 (Box 1)
- Personal Correspondence of T. P. and Ida (Robertson) Abernethy 1930, 1932-1935, 1937 (Box 1)
- Personal Correspondence of T. P. and Ida (Robertson) Abernethy 1940-1943, 1945, 1949 (Box 1)
- Personal Correspondence of T. P. and Ida (Robertson) Abernethy 1953, 1955-1959 (Box 2)
- Personal Correspondence of T. P. and Ida (Robertson) Abernethy 1963, 1965-1969 (Box 2)
- Personal Correspondence of T. P. and Ida (Robertson) Abernethy 1970-1972 (Box 2)
- Personal Correspondence of T. P. and Ida (Robertson) Abernethy Jan., Dec., & n. d. (Box 2)
- Articles, Speeches, & Book Reviews by T. P. Abernethy 1965, [1970] & n. d. (Box 2)
- Introduction to Harper Torchbook edition of Thomas Jefferson's Notes on the State of Va. By T. P. Abernethy 1963 (Box 2)
- Bibliographical Notes for The South In The New Nation; Index for The Formative Period In Alabama; "Sources of Information" for Southern Frontiers of the War of 1812[1961, 1965 & 1968] (Box 2)
- Research Material n. d. (Box 2)
- Articles and Stories by [Ida (Robertson) Abernethy?] n. d. (Box 2)
- Papers re: Corcoran Department of History, University of Virginia 1969-1971 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous Papers 1918, 1925, 1934, 1936, 1961, 1963, 1964, 1966, 1968, & n. d. (Box 2)
- Photograph of engraving of Barracks for Hessian Prisoners in Albemarle Co., Va. n. d. (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous Programs, Pamphlets, and Printed Material 1937, 1940, 1945, 1947, 1951, 1960-1961, 1969-1970, 1972 & n. d. (Box 2)
- Newspaper and Periodical Clippings and Articles by and about T. P., Ida (Robertson) Abernethy and the Abernethy family 1926, 1927, 1938, 1940, 1945, 1954, 1956, 1962, 1964-1965, 1969 & n. d. (Box 2)
- Newspaper and Periodical Clippings re: Politics 1962-1965, 1967, 1975 & n. d. (Box 2)
- Newspaper Clippings re: Psychic Phenomena 1963-1964 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings 1958, 1961 1963, 1964, 1966, 1967, & n. d. (Box 2)